<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<post>
  <author>mwrock</author>
  <title>Bug fixes and enhancements included in RequestReduce 1.7.26</title>
  <description />
  <content>&lt;p&gt;I usually don&amp;rsquo;t blog on bug fix releases. However the bug fix release I deployed today addresses a couple serious bugs (albeit edge cases) and their fixes forced a few significant enhancements I want to call out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Css that reference the same image twice may produce sprite sheets that cut out some of the images at the end of the sprite sheet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The logic that determines which css selectors can be included within another css selector sometimes breaks with child selectors (eg. .parent-class &amp;gt; .child).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upgraded to v4.44 of the MS Ajax Minifier which addresses a bug that causes a JS error in IE8 with Google&amp;rsquo;s Prettify.js. While IE8 throws an error, all other browsers suffer from the fact that this bug essentially breaks the intentions of prettify.js.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RequestReduce was not handling @font-face urls or some data URIs. These are now supported.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were other bugs but these are the really important ones worth mentioning. At work (Microsoft MSDN and Technet web properties) we are preparing for our February release and there have been a couple minor issues raised in addition to the bugs above that have forced the following enhancements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;RequestReduce now handles background-position properties that use pixels, percentages or the directional attributes of top, left, right, center, bottom. Previously, RequestReduce did not consider percentage values or positive pixel units.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some tweaks to the nQuant quantizer parameters increase the quality of the images without sacrificing file size. While RequestReduce generally produces high quality png8 sprites, there are rare cases where images may appear grainy or overly opaque. Today&amp;rsquo;s fix addresses most of these instances. There may still be times where image quality is sub par. This is most likely to happen in very smooth gradients that has a lot of variance in transparency levels. The best way to deal with these is to either disable the image quantization or to decrease the spriteColorCount setting. The fewer colors that the nQuant quantizer has to reduce to 255, the higher the quality of the final image. There is really no hard fast rule here. RequestReduce defaults to 5000, but depending on your images, 10,000 may be fine or you may need to reduce to 2000.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thanks to &lt;a href="https://github.com/PureKrome"&gt;PureKrome&lt;/a&gt;, the RequestReduce dashboard is a little easier on the eyes when displaying lists of urls and it includes exception info for failed requests. I really like this and it improved my quality of life doing some debugging last night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Added a API hook to allow one to transform the absolute url generated by RequestReduce. A popular application of this is to add prefixed subdomains to CDN hosts to allow browsers to load more content at the same time. See the &lt;a href="https://github.com/mwrock/RequestReduce/wiki/The-RequestReduce-Api"&gt;API Wiki&lt;/a&gt; for details.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Upgraded the SassAndCoffee dependency to 2.0.2. This eliminates some of the x64 instability issues of the former version and uses the new IE Chakra JS engine if available. It no longer uses V8.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content>
  <ispublished>True</ispublished>
  <isdeleted>False</isdeleted>
  <iscommentsenabled>True</iscommentsenabled>
  <pubDate>2012-01-15 22:18:00</pubDate>
  <lastModified>2012-01-15 22:18:30</lastModified>
  <raters>0</raters>
  <rating>0</rating>
  <slug>Bug-fixes-and-enhancements-included-in-RequestReduce-1726</slug>
  <tags />
  <comments>
    <comment id="22fedabe-22df-4016-b309-ab2f2a31b64c" parentid="00000000-0000-0000-0000-000000000000" approved="False" spam="True" deleted="False">
      <date>2013-07-15 20:50:10</date>
      <author>0800allergy.com</author>
      <email>merissa.corral@gmail.com</email>
      <country />
      <ip>195.190.13.198</ip>
      <moderatedby>App_Code.Extensions.StopForumSpam</moderatedby>
      <avatar />
      <content>Greetings! Very helpful advice within this article! It&amp;#39;s the little changes that produce the biggest changes. Thanks for sharing!

Feel free to surf to my web blog phen375 ( 0800allergy.com - http://0800allergy.com/2012/11/28/trouble-free-products-for-is-phen375-safe-around-the-uk/ )</content>
    </comment>
  </comments>
  <categories>
    <category>2f8206f0-95a4-449e-bf74-3b2cb761de04</category>
  </categories>
  <notifications />
</post>