<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<post>
  <author>mwrock</author>
  <title>Being Nice</title>
  <description />
  <content>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.mattwrock.com/image.axd?picture=friends.png"&gt;&lt;img style="background-image: none; border-bottom: 0px; border-left: 0px; margin: 0px 10px 0px 0px; padding-left: 0px; padding-right: 0px; display: inline; border-top: 0px; border-right: 0px; padding-top: 0px" title="friends" border="0" alt="friends" src="http://www.mattwrock.com/image.axd?picture=friends_thumb.png" width="404" height="306" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;One of qualities that I think make a great Software Development Engineer not to mention a good human being is the ability to be nice. In fact if I had to list the top 5 things that have helped me in my career, being nice would be one of them. I’m not saying that I have been particularly successful in the art of being nice (yes, it is an art) and I can think of far too many times when I was not nice, but I have made being nice a guiding principle from which I draw to color my decisions and actions and it is an incredibly powerful tool. This may be obvious and if you are thinking the same, that’s a good sign for you and your employer. One may think that it’s a shame that such a concept even deserves a blog post but alas…&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;The world has far too many meanies&lt;/h2&gt;  &lt;p&gt;I came head to head with this reality many many moons ago when I worked as a waiter. Up until this point I was certainly aware that there were a good share of not nice and downright mean and inconsiderate people in the world. However, I thought they were a small minority. Waiting on tables for a “Just a notch above Denny’s scale” restaurant quickly brought home the reality that there are a lot more unpleasant people than I had ever thought. I had never suspected that there could be so many rude, inpatient, and down right awfully behaved adults among me.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0px 10px 0px 0px" src="http://americanimage.net/mediac/400_0/media/PlayNice72.jpg" /&gt;Well fortunately I run into fewer not nice people per capita in the Software industry, but they are there. However, this post is not really intended to focus on mean programmers, but about developers who go the extra mile to be nice. Sure a lot of us can be nice or at least&amp;#160; tolerable, but some of us are lacking when it comes to being nice backed with intention.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;Being nice adds value&lt;/h2&gt;  &lt;p&gt;When I think of the top dozen people that have been a true joy to work with and taught me the most in terms of leadership and software best practices, they were all nice. Being nice provides a wonderful delivery mechanism for all sorts of value beyond just being nice. While I believe there are rare exceptions, being nice is the best means by which you can color your personal interactions and effectively drive home quality. Of course quality can certainly be delivered without being nice – certainly without going out of one’s way to be nice, but I guarantee you that if you add niceness to your interactions, it will positively influence your ability to drive home your philosophies, to promote adoption of your software and to unlock career opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Going back to thinking about the people in the industry I admire who are either “celebrity” types I don’t personally know or people I have worked extensively with, their ability to be nice really is more than a nuance, it a concrete thing about their character that is obvious and ends up being something that I specifically call out as being something I like about that person and motivates me to want to interact with them again.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;It has to be genuine&lt;/h2&gt;  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img style="margin: 0px 10px 0px 0px" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_eVUWcwzqgK8/SqQasw9SEHI/AAAAAAAADzs/28GwfMbJ6b4/s400/awkward+hug.jpg" /&gt;The last thing I want is for someone to interpret this as a Machiavellian attempt to gain favor from others or get others to do your bidding. We have all been exposed to those types. You’ll see this a lot in recruiters or sales individuals. You can often smell the insincerity. They like to say your name a lot in a way that makes you want to shower with a wire brush after each utterance.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;No. When I think about these nice value packed individuals, they are nice because it’s a core part of who they are. They didn’t just read a pamphlet of nice pointers. They are nice because they want to be nice and they enjoy being nice.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;Nice. A definition.&lt;/h2&gt;  &lt;p&gt;So what is this nice I speak of? Perhaps nice is not the best word for the point I am trying to get across. I’m talking about more than just good manners but I’m not necessarily talking about Jesus Christ either. Nor am I talking about Santa Clause. But he does seem super super nice.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;I’m taking about an intentional, proactive means of communicating and relating with others that seeks out their benefit (and perhaps among several other benefits) and is ignorant of status or other artificial cast systems in your organization. Interacting with others as an equal and trying to be helpful. Here’s a small but perhaps tangible example. I’m talking about the difference between someone that answers all their IMs with “Hey”&amp;#160; or “Yeah” compared with Hi Matt. This can be incredibly subtle. Here is why this example resonates with me. I used to work with a developer in Chile. Remotely of course. He was incredibly competent and he was very nice. He never sent me flowers or showed huge concern if I was sick but there was a tone to every IM conversation and email he sent. A tone of sincere helpfulness. Every initial answer to an IM was “Hi Matt!” His emails were often genius. But there was no ego in them, they were plain, to the point, clear and thorough and had an air of “I hope that this is helpful” to them. Everyone thought he was nice but then no one would say, “That Fernando, he is one of the nicest guys I know.” He was pretty ordinary but an example of how simply being nice can go a long long way.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;In an an environment where the dev team hated to work with offshore vendors, everyone loved working with this person. He was one of the most highly paid engineers on staff. At the time he reported to me, he made more money than I made and he was worth every penny. In large part because he was nice. Honestly, when I think back to working with this individual, that was one of his most valuable characteristics. Sure his technical competencies were superb, but colored with his niceness, they were effective as well.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;Can brilliance be an excuse for not being nice?&lt;/h2&gt;  &lt;p&gt;I know there are some who will argue that although being nice is indeed a desirable quality, There are some who are certainly not nice but they are “brilliant.” I agree. There are some truly brilliant minds who are not nice. Yes, these people have often managed to be successful and influential. But generally speaking, I’m not interested in working with them. I may value a lot of what they have to say, but I’m not particularly keen to really engage with them.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;When it comes to recruiting, I simply will not hire someone (or suggest hiring someone) who comes across as being a jerk. While we should strive to produce quality software and attract&amp;#160; candidates who are great problem solvers and solution architects, above that I want quality of life. I want to work with others who are pleasant to be around. Its good for me, its good for the product and its good for the team. Software development competence is easily taught, being nice is built on a lifestyle developed over a lifetime&amp;#160; Having interviewed hundreds of candidates, if I could put candidates into buckets of not nice, some what nice (basically not not nice) and candidates who were truly nice. The ones in the not nice bucket just don't get hired, the somewhat nice group have a fair chance of being hired proportional to their standard competencies. The nice ones often get hired and people are excited to hire them and look for ways to justify hiring them. Don’t get me wrong. They have to show promise as developers, but being nice is like the Malt Vinegar on fish and chips. It’s the more than subtle nuance that makes me say Mmmm.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Things that make me go Mmm (Things that make me go Mmm) Things that make me go Mmm, yeah-eah-eah.Things that make me go Mmm, Mmm, Mmm (Mmm). Things that make me go Mmm.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;I apologize. That was embarrassing. I will now commence with the blog post.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;Compare two developers next to each other, one is difficult to be around but extremely competent and the other is very pleasant and competent but not as much as the former. I would argue that the potential of the second individual’s success is greater than the first.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;h2&gt;The consequences of impolite behavior is often more destructive than valuable&lt;/h2&gt;  &lt;p&gt;As software engineers, many of us were not popular when we were younger. We escaped to a world of code and video games to avoid others and feed our spirit with challenges and opportunities for private success. Many of us were not stars on the soccer field. We were asked to kick the ball out (I was) instead of risking what we might actually do with that ball in the extremely unlikely event that we manage to actually gain control of the ball at all (I never did). &lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_AXhWXW1FFeA/Sq41y_P5wqI/AAAAAAAAEMA/FdidLyRocxo/s400/kayne_taylor.jpg" /&gt;So it should come as no surprise that many of us share the urge to put others down in order to enhance our own sense of lacking self importance. Just spend a day reading your technically saturated twitter feed. There is a lot more complaining and snark than truly helpful tweets. But I’d ask anyone to think back on their own snarky remarks. The ones they thought were true gems. They really put a person or followers of a particular technology in their place. A place much inferior to your own views. Now consider how valuable the comment was. How many were likely to change their attitudes or stumble upon better practices after hearing such remarks? Did the remark have an impact? Yeah it felt good to say at the time, but looking back did it add or subtract from your net value as a contributor to your craft? I’m gonna guess that it deducted more value than it added. At least that is my own experience.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;When I think back on some of the scenarios where I publicly put someone down or spoke condescendingly to someone as I complained about their technology or practices, in the end I really only made myself feel good and look bad at the same time. And none of those moments were moments that “made a difference” in moving my team, my values or my career forward.&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p&gt;I hope you have found this to be a nice post.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  <ispublished>True</ispublished>
  <isdeleted>False</isdeleted>
  <iscommentsenabled>True</iscommentsenabled>
  <pubDate>2012-01-16 02:02:07</pubDate>
  <lastModified>2012-01-30 14:53:00</lastModified>
  <raters>0</raters>
  <rating>0</rating>
  <slug>Being-Nice</slug>
  <tags />
  <comments>
    <comment id="4664abf0-f608-4fa8-be59-d0912998ede6" parentid="00000000-0000-0000-0000-000000000000" approved="True" spam="False" deleted="False">
      <date>2012-01-16 05:17:03</date>
      <author>Herbert</author>
      <email>herbert.leberbauer@gmx.at</email>
      <country />
      <ip>213.174.252.248</ip>
      <avatar />
      <content>Hi Matt,

I loved to read this post. I found it &amp;quot;by accident&amp;quot;, but I am really glad about your words (of truth) - it&amp;#39;s my point of view, that there is more to life and work than performance, money, knowledge, bits and bytes etc... There also has to be the human touch in everything - that&amp;#39;s what makes our work human. For the non-human products we invent machines.

So go your way - it&amp;#39;s a good one - and be an idol for those who will follow.

bye and many greetings from Austria
Herbert</content>
    </comment>
    <comment id="41e18ab8-ed0b-4b0a-945a-82eaf707c80c" parentid="00000000-0000-0000-0000-000000000000" approved="True" spam="False" deleted="False">
      <date>2012-01-16 09:25:51</date>
      <author>Matthew Manela</author>
      <email>mmanela@gmail.com</email>
      <country />
      <ip>98.203.252.118</ip>
      <avatar />
      <content>I completely agree with your post. 

Nice people have an almost infectious affect on people around them. They make people happier and happy people do better work. Having a conversation with a truly nice person leaves an sense contentment and makes you want to be nicer.

</content>
    </comment>
    <comment id="b3d54e5e-c6eb-4d20-b94c-ae3bcb5681f8" parentid="00000000-0000-0000-0000-000000000000" approved="True" spam="False" deleted="False">
      <date>2012-01-17 05:58:05</date>
      <author>shadowmoss</author>
      <email>shadowmoss@gmail.com</email>
      <country />
      <ip>173.164.27.254</ip>
      <avatar />
      <content>I stumbled onto your Grandfather&amp;#39;s blog over a year ago.  I read his writing with great enjoyment, even though I do not know any of your family.  I&amp;#39;m here because he recommended this post in his blog.  I think you nailed the reason I so look forward to reading his blog, he is totally nice.  And, it seems, the apples haven&amp;#39;t fallen far from the tree.</content>
    </comment>
    <comment id="e0e1de22-2049-453a-9848-8d638f902577" parentid="00000000-0000-0000-0000-000000000000" approved="True" spam="False" deleted="False">
      <date>2012-01-17 08:53:03</date>
      <author>Matt Wrock</author>
      <email>matt@mattwrock.com</email>
      <country />
      <ip>50.46.255.50</ip>
      <avatar />
      <content>@shadowmoss: My grandfather is indeed one of the nicest people I know. If I at all come across being similar at all to him, then that is one of the best indicators I know of that I might be doing something right. I mean that with all sincerity. Thanks for your very kind comment.</content>
    </comment>
    <comment id="a2a69796-7d7f-4796-bab8-fb0a20563ea8" parentid="00000000-0000-0000-0000-000000000000" approved="True" spam="False" deleted="False">
      <date>2012-01-17 09:26:38</date>
      <author>Erik</author>
      <email>erik@daedtech.com</email>
      <country />
      <ip>65.167.132.200</ip>
      <avatar />
      <content>I like your take here, particularly where you talk about Twitter.  So much of technical collaboration, especially online, seems to be more about oneupsmanship than sincere helping.  Because of this, I tend to remember people who respond to a question I might ask with, &amp;quot;that&amp;#39;s an interesting idea, but here are some potential issues I could see with your approach&amp;quot; much more than people who respond with &amp;quot;that&amp;#39;s stupid, and here&amp;#39;s why.&amp;quot;  

In both cases, I get the answer/feedback that helps me, but in the former case, I might go out of my way to subscribe to the person&amp;#39;s blog/stackoverflow feed/tweets/etc.  In the latter case, not so much.</content>
    </comment>
    <comment id="0d223d6b-caa5-4af3-b5d0-a6107edc9102" parentid="00000000-0000-0000-0000-000000000000" approved="True" spam="False" deleted="False">
      <date>2012-01-17 11:51:26</date>
      <author>Mike Monson</author>
      <email>michaelmonson@att.net</email>
      <country />
      <ip>38.99.3.34</ip>
      <avatar />
      <content>This is a brilliant blog by a very nice man.
You know my father (your grandfather) used to say something that shows his sentiments and that I think must have rubbed off on you:

&amp;quot;Before speaking, ask yourself three questions: is it kind? is it true? is it necessary? If the answer is no to any of those questions then keep quiet.&amp;quot; 

</content>
    </comment>
    <comment id="5a5928df-d304-48a3-9403-2a592d07c8bc" parentid="00000000-0000-0000-0000-000000000000" approved="True" spam="False" deleted="False">
      <date>2012-01-30 05:24:05</date>
      <author>Mickael Istria</author>
      <email>mickael.istria@gmail.com</email>
      <country />
      <ip>80.14.188.138</ip>
      <avatar />
      <content>You should read this study:  http://nd.edu/~cba/Nice--JPSPInPress.pdf , that concludes, on page 66 and 67 that nasty people earn more money. Sad but true.
I also agree with your post, so a conclusion of both can be &amp;quot;Successful software developer earn less money&amp;quot;.</content>
    </comment>
    <comment id="63b9f12d-77ff-40bd-bafd-349c6c1e05ce" parentid="00000000-0000-0000-0000-000000000000" approved="True" spam="False" deleted="False">
      <date>2012-01-30 05:41:06</date>
      <author>Matt Wrock</author>
      <email>matt@mattwrock.com</email>
      <country />
      <ip>50.46.255.50</ip>
      <avatar />
      <content>@Mickael: Interesting. Didn&amp;#39;t read the whole thing but it brings up a interesting point: Can you be nice AND disagreeable? The study focuses on &amp;quot;agreeableness&amp;quot; which can certainly be interpreted as nice. I for one think it is nice when people agree with me :) which makes you nice. Isn&amp;#39;t that nice? 

I do think its possible and important to be nice and disagreeable. To a great extent, one has to be disagreeable in order to influence change but it would be interesting to study the styles of disagreeableness. Does disagreeable imply abrasive? Maybe the study explores this but I would tend to think that one who can be disagreeable but still be nice may be more effective.

I&amp;#39;m sure there are exceptions. Steve Jobs is probably a great anti-case study here. Definitely not nice. Definitely successful and a great influencer of positive change whom I respect a bunch. If he was nice would he have been even more effective? Maybe or quite likely maybe not.

I&amp;#39;m really speaking in general terms here that if engineers could put more focus on being nice, it will serve them and others well.</content>
    </comment>
    <comment id="e0e4463c-6c25-492c-9993-21ea6a218f7b" parentid="00000000-0000-0000-0000-000000000000" approved="True" spam="False" deleted="False">
      <date>2012-01-30 05:53:00</date>
      <author>Herbert</author>
      <email>herbert.leberbauer@gmx.at</email>
      <country />
      <ip>213.174.252.248</ip>
      <avatar />
      <content>@Mickael: I found your post and the link attached very interesting, but let me say two thing:
1st: Studies are always retrospective - so it is on us, to change the outcome of such studies in the future! I am not interested, that I have to tell my children: If you want to be successful in live, don&amp;#39;t be nice!
2nd: Despite I am not a native speaker of the english/american language, to me, there is a difference between being nice and being disagreeable. And this difference is vital, because I think it is the &amp;quot;secret&amp;quot; of successful nice people, that they are disagreeable too, if it is needed.

Maybe it should be said, that being nice, does not mean, to kiss someone&amp;#39;s ass. (Sorry for that bad language!)

cheers
Herbert</content>
    </comment>
  </comments>
  <categories />
  <notifications>
    <email>herbert.leberbauer@gmx.at</email>
    <email>yogita@yahoo.com</email>
    <email>shadowmoss@gmail.com</email>
    <email>michaelmonson@att.net</email>
    <email>mickael.istria@gmail.com</email>
    <email>tclearbra@gmail.com</email>
    <email>mike.james@business-inc.co.uk</email>
    <email>phillip.macon@yahoo.com</email>
    <email>erectz@hotmail.com</email>
  </notifications>
</post>